In nature, males will do anything to
mate with a female. They'll offer gifts,
engage in elaborate dances, but most
frequently,
they'll beat the hell out of each other.
But the combat doesn't stop there. The
winner of the fight on the outside must
still face another much more brutal
battle on the inside, where microscopic
wars lead to millions of casualties, and
where physical and chemical weaponry is
developed in a high-speed militaristic
arms race. all inside the female
reproductive tract. Today, we're
covering sperm competition in nature,
every surreal sperm adaptation it's
caused across animals, and the
surprising effects it's had on human
evolution. So, come with me as we
explore this, but don't come against me,
cuz my sperm will beat the hell out of
your sperm. Sperm competition is the
result of exactly that, competition. I
mean, these elephant seals aren't
exactly having a friendly contest, are
they? The two bulls ram their bodies
into each other like a giant thumb war
and viciously bite each other's noses
and necks, drawing blood until only one
is left standing or flopping, I guess.
See, the winner gets sole control over a
harum of 20 to 50 females, able to mate
with any and all of them so freely and
carelessly that they sometimes
accidentally crush the females and even
their own babies to death. while the
loser has to hang his derpy nose in
shame and flop away with zero
reproductive potential on the table. The
official term for the dominant elephant
seal is beachmaster, which is very fun.
So, shout out to whoever came up with
that. However, none of this is fun for
the beach losers, who aren't strong
enough to ever think about challenging
the current heavyweight champion and can
only hover around and watch. But they
haven't given up entirely. See, hovering
elephant seals are frequently seen
trying to mate with females near the
edge of the herum and then flee as
quickly as possible. And while this
effort is typically thwarted by the
beach master quite easily, getting to
reproduce is worth so much that
non-dominant males will spend their
entire breeding season lying around
subjecting themselves to this cruel
cuckoldry all for the slight chance that
they may be able to sneak in and steal a
mating. That's how steep male male
competition is. Thus, sneak mating in
this way is a very common strategy in
nature. Watch as this brown trout flies
in, quickly ejaculates all over a
female's eggs, then swims away. Also,
notice how this male is so much smaller
than this one. These are two males from
a couple different species. As you can
see, there are two distinct forms within
each. There are the large garter males,
which win over females through brawn the
oldfashioned way, and small sneaker
males, which use their small size to
quickly steal mings from larger fish.
Not every male can be the biggest and
strongest. And so lineages of
non-dominant males separately evolve an
alternative peak male physique that
emphasizes stealth and speed over size
and strength to still fight for a chance
their own way. Sneak mating is
interesting because it circumvents the
traditional view of malemale competition
where one male is the gigachad who wins
the female and gets to pass on his genes
while the other is the loser that dies
forever alone. Instead, a dominant male
can mate with a female and then another
male can sneak in and inject sperm into
her. Anyways, imagine doing all that
work to win over your dream girl and
things are going well and you're trying
for a kid. Then a smurf runs up and
somehow bangs her and disappears. And
now when she says she's pregnant, you
can't be sure that the baby isn't going
to pop out a little blue. Losing your
guaranteed paternity in this way would
suck. And so there arises a new
competition. Sneak mating versus mate
guarding. It's a behavior seen in nearly
all mammals, birds, insects, and fish,
where males physically guard a female to
deny rivals an opportunity with her.
Most animals do this by just chasing
other males away. But this can be taken
much further. In red veined darters, the
male dragonfly will clasp onto the back
of the female's neck with his tail after
mating with her, staying firmly attached
to her and flying together as a pair,
only releasing after she lays her eggs.
Many animals find ways to physically
plug the female reproductive organ.
Kangaroo semen coagulates shortly after
ejaculation, sealing the female tract
like superglue, preventing future males
from properly mating with her. In giant
wood spiders, males sever their own
genitals, breaking it off to create a
plug. Though in this species, females
can also make their own plugs to prevent
unwanted sex. Redsided garder snakes
deposit a gelatinous plug, sealing the
female cloica. But this gel is also
filled with chemicals that alter her
pherommonal signals, which makes her
less attractive to other males. But
alas, mate guarding doesn't always work.
You can't be 100% vigilant all the time,
especially when life demands other
things of you, like finding food or
running away from predators. So, sneaker
males will inevitably find their way
through. Additionally, females of many
species don't always want to be guarded
and may seek out other males and remove
mating plugs on their own. This may be
after a female notices a different male
of a higher quality after already mating
with one or sometimes females take new
partners to protect themselves from
sexual aggression on the part of their
current partner. And so often times we
have scenarios where multiple males have
injected sperm into a single female. And
when this happens, what decides whose
sperm gets to fertilize the egg? Well,
seems pretty obvious, right? The fastest
sperm should reach the egg first. And
so, males that adapt to have faster
sperm should be more successful. The
midpiece of human sperm is filled with
mitochondria, the say it with me now,
powerhouse of the sperm. Yeah. Which
gives it a lot of energy to whirl its
fleellum at a Michael Phelps pace,
moving at a speed developed over
generations of sperm competition. But
speed isn't everything. If you produce
more sperm, you have more Olympians in
the race. A single human ejaculation
contains anywhere between 40 to 300
million individual sperm. It's simple.
The more sperm you provide, the better
your odds for one of them winning. Male
dunox who recognize a female has already
been mated with will peck at her cloica,
dislodging the semen of the previous
male to ensure that he has more sperm in
the race than the previous male. But the
sperm of the fruitfly, Drosophila bif
fura, goes to much further lengths than
this. Literally like their sperm is
really long. At 5.8 cm or 2.3 in, it's
the longest sperm of any living
organism. For the record, difurca's
average body length is about 3 mm.
Meaning their sperm are about 20 times
longer than their own body, just coiled
up extremely tightly. It's thought that
the reason for this length is that the
female sperm receptacle in fruit flies
is pretty long and there's a competitive
advantage to males with longer sperm.
There are several other weird sperm
types that show up in nature. But before
we get into them, what makes sperm
competition so cool is the vast
diversity in which animals display it,
no matter how microscopic it is. But
zooming out, this wonderful diversity
has been declining as the environment
continues to be destroyed. Let's not
give up hope, though. I believe that
together we can change this, which is
why I'm partnering with my friends at
Planet Wild. Planet Wild is a 13,000
member community-f funed organization
that helps rewests, protect endangered
species, and clean up our oceans all
across the world. Think of it as
crowdfunding for nature. Every month,
they fund a new conservation project
with their carefully selected partners.
Their latest project really inspired me.
They're protecting the Amazon
rainforest, the most biodiverse place on
Earth and also one of the largest carbon
sinks on the planet. Crucial for
preventing extreme climate disasters
globally. Planet Wild is helping
indigenous tribes preserve their land by
funding forest patrols, providing
equipment for stopping the spread of
fires, and attempting to get the region
legally recognized as a UNESCO biosphere
reserve and world heritage site. It's
just one of several amazing initiatives
that you can support and be a part of
through Planet Wild's community. I
myself am a member of Planet Wild. I
have always loved the natural world.
It's why I make these videos and why I'm
pursuing my PhD in biology. But I've
always been anxious about making sure my
money goes directly to the right causes.
On Planet Wild's YouTube channel, you'll
get a fun, educational, 100% transparent
video every month showing what your
contributions help to achieve, the
impact each project has, and the
long-term outcome. As a YouTuber, I'm
actually very impressed by the quality
of these videos. I really encourage you
to check them out in the link below. You
can also get updates on their app,
interact with the Planet Wild community,
and receive unique mission badges for
your support. So, if you want to make a
difference, scan the QR code on screen
or click the link in the description so
you can be a part of the solution. The
first 150 people to sign up using my
code, DAN8, will get their first month
on me because I want you to see for
yourself that Planet Wild is an
organization worth supporting. You can
sign up for a flexibly priced membership
based on what you can afford. Every
dollar counts. The best part, you'll see
your impact in less than 30 days. And if
you don't feel like supporting Planet
Wild anymore, don't worry, you can
cancel anytime. Join a community of
people who care about nature and want to
protect it, not with empty words, but
with real, measurable action. Let's make
a difference together. Back to the
video. Pasarine bird sperm are twisted
in a helical shape like a drill that
improves motility. Motility isn't the
same as mobility. Here, it refers to the
ability to move within a specific
substance rather than a general medium.
For example, some sperm may be able to
move faster in water, but not so fast
through the often viscous fluid of the
female reproductive tract in certain
species. Quacking frogs also have
twisted sperm, and they show the
advantage of this quite nicely. The more
twisted sperm that moves at slower
velocities are found to exhibit more
fertilization success than faster sperm
that's less twisted. Actually, in a 2009
experiment, slower twisted sperm even
outco competed faster twisted sperm for
some reason. So, it seems there are many
factors besides speed that determine the
winner of the sperm race, many of which
are unclear. Partially, it's because
it's hard to observe sperm in the first
place. But, it's especially tricky when
every single organism has completely
different sperm competition dynamics,
which leads to different shapes and
behavior in their sperm. However, what
is clear is the importance of sperm
competition on male behaviors. Not only
are mate guarding, mating plugs, and the
cleaning out of the genitals all direct
consequences of trying to minimize it,
many animals adjust the amount of semen
they produce based on the amount of
sperm competition they perceive. This is
called ejaculate economics or prudent
sperm allocation. In Norway rats, males
that mated in a cage with only a female
produced significantly less sperm than
males that mated in a cage with a female
and another male present behind a
plastic screen. Sneaker males in fish
and squid are found to have better sperm
swimming speed, persistence, and
lifespan. when compared to dominant
males in the same species. Given that
the entire sneaker male strategy hinges
on engaging in sperm competition rather
than traditional competition, it makes
sense they would invest more resources
into higher quality sperm. There's even
some research that measured ejaculate
size in humans and found that males that
reported to spend more time away from
their partner and thought that she may
be exposed to other men produced more
sperm than males that spent less time
away from their partner and felt less
about the presence of other men in her
life. Now, this research is a bit
contentious. There could be a lot of
other factors when it comes to human
sex. But whether or not this is true in
humans, prudent sperm allocation is a
phenomenon that's clearly observed
across the animal kingdom. But male
behavior is only one part of the
equation. It turns out females have a
lot of control over what happens inside
them as well. In separate studies,
researchers mated guppies and crickets
with random mates and with mates that
were genetically related to them. It's
well known that inbreeding tends to lead
to, let's say, nonfavorable evolutionary
outcomes. And so it would be in a
female's best interest to use a
stranger's sperm rather than a siblings.
And that's exactly what they found. In
both experiments, females biased their
offspring to be more often descended
from non-related mates rather than their
relatives, even when mated with both to
the same degree, suggesting an internal
mechanism in females to avoid inbreeding
by favoring sperm that's less
genetically related to them. It's
thought that there are proteins present
in the reproductive tract and on the
surface of the egg that are responsible
for this. Human eggs release chemo
attractant signals that are only picked
up by about 30% of sperm. And these
chosen sperm show greater genetic
compatibility with the egg. This is an
example of cryptic female choice where a
female influences which and whose sperm
gets to fertilize her eggs. As I said
earlier, females in many species prefer
to take multiple mates. And this is
something that Darwin never understood.
In his original theory of sexual
selection, he postulated that females
should want one mate with a focus on
quality while males should be the one
that want to spread their seed as far as
possible. The theory makes a lot of
sense except it could never explain the
widespread existence of polyandry when
females take multiple partners. But
cryptic female choice can account for
this. There's no worry of lowquality
offspring when at the end of the day you
can simply select the highest quality
sperm internally. In sand lizards, the
more males that a female mates with, the
lower their rates of hatching failures
and the better their rates of offspring
survival. In some birds, like chickens,
gulls, and dunox, females are known to
straight up eject the sperm of males
they don't like. Beetles and flies can
commit spermicide, releasing a chemical
weapon that degrades sperm within
themselves, which they do more often
after mating with lowquality males. in
gelatas and some species of rodent,
females can even terminate their
pregnancy after fertilization. Just as
male male competition isn't over after
sex, neither is female choice. So sperm
aren't only in a race against the sperm
of other males, but also in conflict
with the female who may consider them
lowquality. Much like in actual war,
soldiers don't only face their
adversaries, but the very environment in
which they fight. But much like an
actual war, teamwork makes possible what
one man could only dream of alone. The
sperm of wood mice have this strange
hook on their head. One quick look under
a microscope reveals its function. It
allows the sperm to connect together
from hook to hook and hook to tail like
a bunch of interlocking safety clips.
These groups can consist of two to
thousands of individual sperm forming a
massive sperm train that charges forward
in unison. The shared momentum and shape
of the train allow the sperm to push
through the wood mouse reproductive
tract like a giant battering ram,
allowing them to be 50% more motile than
a sperm swimming solo. This is an
example of sperm cooperation, an
altruistic behavior where several sperm
band together, potentially sacrificing
their own chance for success for the
sake of a few to prosper. And they can
do this because they're genetically
related. What's important in evolution
is that your genetic material gets
passed down. So sperm of the same male
don't have to be selfish and compete
with each other. Instead, they can put
their forces together like a massive
spirit bomb, sending one to live a life
for the millions left behind. In diving
beetles, sperm cooperation is seen in a
number of forms. They sometimes pair
together side by side or they form a
chain structure called a ruo where the
head of one sperm is nestled into a
hollow pocket at the base of the head of
a different sperm. These can get
extremely long and even involve multiple
different kinds of sperm. The kamicazi
sperm hypothesis posits that some sperm
aren't meant for fertilization and
instead to sacrifice themselves in order
to incapacitate the sperm of other
males. And while this has been widely
discredited in humans, it may hold true
in some snails which have two or three
sperm types. There are the fertile uerm
which operate as normal and the
infertile parasperm which have other
functions for sperm competition. In
gastropods, these can be large carrier
sperm which userm can attach to for
transport likely meant to improve
motility similar to a sperm train. And
there are the lancet type sperm which
are thought to be used as chemical
weapons. They contain several digestive
enzymes which may be released in the
reproductive tract to kill off the sperm
of other males. Sperm heteromorphism
describes the simultaneous production of
more than one distinct type of sperm.
And this is another one of those cases
where everything is a little unclear.
Butterflies and stockeyed flies have
long um which contain a nucleus and
short parisperm without a nucleus that
are seemingly useless. In ground
beetles, parasperm are large and even
contain genetic information yet still
seem to be unusable for fertilization or
anything else. Sculpin fish have large
discshaped sperm which again do nothing.
Considering the consistent shapes and
makeups of these supposedly useless
parasperm, it's possible that they have
functions that we haven't detected yet
or once had a function that is no longer
necessary. That or they're produced
alongside userm as cheap filler or
simply by accident. Not everything in
evolution needs to have a purpose after
all. But still, this is an area that
needs a lot more research before we swim
to any conclusions.
Hey, you know what would be a real
winning sperm thing to do? Subscribing
and leaving a comment. I have a feeling
this video won't do as well as my last
few just given the weird topic. So, if
you're enjoying this, say like and a
comment would go a long way. Thanks.
Okay, I want to end this video by
talking about the effects sperm
competition has had on human evolution.
But first, there are some really cool
examples of sperm competition that I
couldn't elegantly fit earlier in the
video that I want to quickly highlight
because they're insane. These sperm,
complete with two barbs sticking out of
it, are found in flatworms. Flatworms
are hermaphroditic, meaning they have
both male and female reproductive parts.
Some species go through the process of
penis fencing, striking and parrying
each other with the tip of their
genitals until one lands a hit and
injects their sperm. Sometimes flatworms
will suck sperm out of their own
reproductive tract if they don't like
their mate, a showing of cryptic female
choice. However, their spiky sperm has
adapted to prevent this. The barbs work
to lodge themselves in, sort of like a
fish hook or an arrowhead, ensuring that
they can only be pushed deeper and not
pulled out. In roundorms or nematodes,
this is a bit different. Their sperm
don't even swim. They crawl with a
pseudopod exactly as an amoeba would. In
the genus canor heepditis, the sperm can
be very dangerous to females, sometimes
busting out of the reproductive tract,
invading other parts of the body. This
is thought to be the result of very high
sperm competition amongst the males,
which the females have needed to adapt
to in order to handle. When
crossbreeding a canorhabditis male to a
female of a different neode species, the
sperm completely ravages her insides,
marching around and killing her or
vastly ruining her ability to reproduce.
Just goes to show how varying degrees of
sperm competition, even within closely
related species, can cause sperm to
evolve and operate at completely
different intensities. And lastly, when
you add the sperm of a leaf cutter ant's
seinal fluid, the invader sperm will
quickly die. It's a result of intense
sperm competition, using chemical
degradance to obliterate rival armies of
sperm. However, leaf cutter queens need
to mate with several males all in one
day before burrowing into the ground and
producing children for 20 to 30 years.
That means that they need to store
usable sperm within themselves for that
long. If the contents of the various
male fluids were still harmful to each
other, this wouldn't be possible. And so
inside the queen, she secretes an
antidote, destroying the proteins in the
semen that target rival sperm,
effectively cancelling out the sperm
competition that the males worked so
hard to evolve. Okay, we've covered more
about sperm competition than sheets have
been covered in sperm. It's finally time
to ask, how has sperm competition
impacted human evolution? More
specifically, how intense is sperm
competition in humans compared to other
animals? Well, the first place we should
look is down towards the male situation.
Our testes size is larger than most
other primates. And this is correlated
with larger volumes of sperm per
ejaculation, something that is obviously
helpful for sperm competition. In line
with this, we also have the largest
penis of all the primates. There's
evidence that injecting semen deeper
into the cervix increases the chance of
siring offspring. So, our relatively big
shafts and balls are both likely the
result of sperm competition. That being
said, we don't have a bulum, a literal
boner that some animals have, which
makes depositing and scooping out sperm
as efficient as possible and tends to be
present in animals with high levels of
sperm competition. So, while we show
greater amounts of sperm competition
than other primates, it seems relatively
moderate compared to animals as a whole.
Supporting this is our own sperm
heteromorphism. Not in sophisticated
parisperm and sperm, but in working
sperm and deformed sperm. It's common to
find human sperm with two heads, two
tails, or just be generally misshapen at
about 10% of the time. This is a lot
higher of a rate than in animals with
high sperm competition, which likely
need to be more exacting in the level of
their sperm quality to be competitively
viable. In naked mole rats, only the
queen and one to three males gets to
reproduce, meaning there's barely any
sperm competition. In support of our
pattern here, 40% of naked mole rat
sperm is so deformed that it's
completely unusable. As a tribal
species, we have a lot of natural
behaviors that prevent sperm
competition. a tendency towards monogamy
or pair bonding is the main one because
it turns sexual rivalries into something
to be settled rather than something to
constantly fight over. It's also good
for our extensive parenting behaviors.
And these evolutionary incentives end up
being built into our customs and taboos.
Taking another mate is now called
cheating. It isn't some primitive way to
improve reproductive success as a male,
but instead a serious social and moral
flaw. It shows you as a bad partner, a
bad parent, a bad member of the tribe.
Still, that doesn't mean sperm
competition is irrelevant to us. Most
people aren't strictly monogous, and
we're still affected by feelings of
jealousy or aggression towards someone
flirting with your partner, etc. And
yeah, our mating system might not be
comparable to animals that form mating
swarms where everyone has sex with
everyone, but it still involves a level
of competition that shapes the way we
are today. Sperm competition is
obviously much more complex than a
simple race. It's a largecale battle on
multiple fronts, never ending yet always
evolving. And that makes your
achievement in winning it all the more
impressive. Thanks for watching.